Guide to the New York City WPA historical survey of Indigenous People of Brooklyn 1977.121
Brooklyn Historical Society
New York City WPA historical survey of Indigenous People of Brooklyn
1939-1940
1600-1940
Brooklyn Historical Society
United States. Works Projects Administration (New York, N.Y.)
MacLeod, William Christie
1977.121
0.5 Linear Feet in one box.
This collection includes drafted sections of "The Indians of Brooklyn in the Days of the Dutch," edited by William Christie MacLeod, which have been organized by subject. It also includes research notes, annotated maps, notes on the orthography of Native American words and names, and typescript copies of 17th century deeds and proclamations.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Deposited by the New York City WPA, 1941.
Arrangement
The materials in this collection have been processed to the folder level. Materials are arranged by type and subject.
Historical note
The New York City Work Projects Administration (WPA) Historical Records Survey was one of the many cultural projects initiated as part of the WPA's federal relief programs from 1935 to 1943. This collection represents the efforts of the Historical Records Survey to collect, transcribe and explain records pertaining to the Native American communities of 17th century Brooklyn.
Archaeological evidence testifies that indigenous people have been living in the region now comprising the five boroughs of New York City for at least 11,500 years. Indigenous people living along the Atlantic seaboard between the Delaware and Hudson valleys refer to themselves as Lenape (people), though the Europeans arriving in the 16th and 17th century called them Delawares. Native Americans of the region are believed to have spoken a variant of Lenape/Delaware dialect known as Munsee. Documented Munsee communities who lived in the area that would eventually become known as Brooklyn included the Marechkawick (sandy place) near present-day Borough Hall, Nayack (point of land), Wichquawanck (sandy bank) at present-day Fort Hamilton, Techkonis (translation unknown) in present-day Gravesend, and Canarsie (grassy place) in present-day Flatlands.
Sources:
Grumet, Robert S. "American Indians," in The Encyclopedia of New York City, ed. Kenneth T. Jackson (New Haven, Conn.: Yale University Press; New York: New York Historical Society, c1995), 25-28.
Scope and Contents
This collection includes drafted sections of "The Indians of Brooklyn in the Days of the Dutch," edited by William Christie MacLeod, as well as research notes, annotated maps, notes on the orthography of Native American words and names, and typescript copies of 17th century deeds and proclamations.
Related Materials
A bound copy of "The Indians of Brooklyn in the Days of the Dutch" is available in our regular non-circulating library collection; see our catalog for more information.
Clippings (information artifacts); Typescripts; Memorandums; Maps; Research notes; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.); Indians of North America |z New York (State) |z Kings County; Canarsie (New York, N.Y.); Flatlands (New York, N.Y.); New Utrecht (New York, N.Y.); Newtown Creek (Kings County-New York County, N.Y.); Nyack (N.Y.); Far Rockaway (New York, N.Y.); Nassau County (N.Y.); Coney Island (New York, N.Y.); Gravesend (New York, N.Y.); Flatbush (New York, N.Y.); Marechkawick; Kaskatensakin; Pagganck; Keskateuw; Wickquawanck; Techkonis; Boswijk; Makeepaca; Keskachane; Esopus; Mechawanienck; Matsepe; Bergen Island; Governors Island; Orthography; Manatus map; Kieft's War, 1643-1645; Penhawis; Stuyvesant, Peter; Cacapoteyno; Couwenhoven family; Hudde, Andries; Van Salee, Anthony Jansen (Janszoon), 1607 – 1667; London, Ambrose; Mechowodt; Kieft, Willem; Mattano; Meijterma; Pennekeck; Seysey; Tienhoven, Cornelis Van; Danckaerts, Jasper; Sluyter, Peter; West India Company; Mohawk; Nayack; Massapeague
- Preface, introduction, bibliography, subject headings and deed list, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Transcribed maps, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Orthography of names, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Dutch timeline, physical descriptions, native physiognomy and bibliographic sketches, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Notes and WPA communication, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Transcripts and Notes on deeds, proclamations and court records, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Land prices, calendars and 'Indian Marks', 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Drafts – Villages: Marechkawick, Wickquawonck and Techkonis, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Drafts – Penhawis, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Drafts – Manatus map, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Drafts – Bushwick, Flatlands, Queens, Gowanus and Coney Island, 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Drafts – Misc., 1939-1940 (Box 1, Folder 12)